a while ago I made a video of the advice
I would give to my younger self if I was
learning to code again on this video I
bring you the roadmap that I would
follow if I was learning to code again
to be able to get a job or to be able to
build and launch a product or service
this roadmap is for people that want to
become full stack developers a full
stack developer is a person that can
build the UI of a service the front end
as well as all the logic security
databases and authentication the backend
plus is also able to put the finished
product on a server the devops I
personally think that aiming to be a
full stack developer is an awesome way
to start it will teach you about and
expose you to all the different parts
and components that make up a web
service you will understand how a
front-end talks to a backend how a
backend talks to a database how cookies
and tokens work how database design
works and when you are done with all of
that you will then need to learn about
servers and how to pull your
applications on them which means that
you will learn a bit of Linux and maybe
you get some experience with AWS and
containers and after you're done with
all that as many people do you might
choose not to stay a full stack
developer and instead you will choose to
specialize in what you like the most
being able to get an overview of the
hold landscape front and the backend
databases and servers will prove very
valuable for your career if you get a
job at a company it will be very easy to
communicate across different areas
because you will have a bird's eye point
of view of how everything connects
together or if you don't want to get a
job and you are a startup founder you
need to become full stack at the start
of your company you're gonna have to do
it all until you can build a prototype
make some money and attract investors
it's going to be a one-man show so let's
get right into it here is the roadmap I
would follow to become a full stack
developer today by the way many if not
all of the concepts on this video you
can learn on our website most of the
courses are for free and you can access
them clicking on the link below it all
starts with HTML and CSS HTML is
incredibly boring but easy to learn it
is the language we use to add content to
our website images text titles lists and
CSS is a design language you will use to
make your website pretty it can make you
suffer if you don't learn it correctly
but once you get comfortable with it you
will be able to build beautiful things
with HTML and CSS you will be building
beautiful but dumb websites websites
that don't do anything apart from
displaying content to start building
smart websites interactive websites or
websites that do something when the user
clicks websites that can get the
geolocation of the user or take a photo
you need JavaScript JavaScript will be
the first programming language that you
will learn it is the language the
browsers speak and it's also your only
option the only program language the
browser understands is Javascript so we
have no choice but to learn it here is
where you will need to build your first
interactive website you will need to use
all the things that you learn from HTML
CSS and JavaScript and build one big
project I made a free Javascript course
where we make a clock a to-do list
weather information with geolocation and
other things if you can complete that
course I would say you are ready to move
on to the next step the next step is to
use JavaScript outside of the browser so
far we have been on the browser which is
fine but JavaScript is much more
powerful than that so now is when you
learn node.js node.js is the same
JavaScript you are used to but outside
of the browser node.js freeze JavaScript
from the prison of the browser it gives
JavaScript the ability to make a web
server to read and create files to talk
to a database to secure password to give
cookies to build a real-time application
node.js is old and it has a huge
Community which means that many people
have built many libraries and Frameworks
that are a standard right now Express is
the most popular node.js web framework
it is used to build the backends it is
super stable it's finished and last I
check it was downloaded more than 100
million times per month after you learn
Express take a look at KOA it is built
by the creator of Express and it was
meant to be its successor many companies
adopted it but many did not if you're
comfortable with Express learning KOA
will take you less than one hour so just
learn it on a weekend and be done with
it if you are building servers with
Express chances are you will be using
eight database to store your data as a
first beginner's database I recommend
mongodb I love SQL I use SQL but mongodb
is a good starting point it has a lower
learning curve than SQL databases
especially if you use Mongoose a node.js
package that helps you talk to
from your JavaScript checkpoint by this
point we know HTML CSS and Java script
on the browser and JavaScript on the
back end with node.js now you have to
ask yourself a question how much do you
like JavaScript did you enjoy node.js if
you did not then Learn Python you cannot
replace JavaScript on the browser with
python but if you want to replace
JavaScript on the back end with
something else now is the time since you
already know JavaScript jumping into
python will not take you that long a
good project to learn and practice
python is to build a web scraper a
crawler a bot that extracts data from a
website I made a free course exactly on
that the link is below After You Learn
Python you will want to build a server
with it the same way you did with
node.js for this you will learn flask
flask is much more easier to learn than
Express so you will have an easier time
with it after you're done with flask you
will see how minimalistic it is and you
might like that or you might not if you
don't if you want a framework that comes
with a lot of opinions and configuration
Nations but that will get you up and
running with users databases admin
panels security among many other things
at record speeds it's time to learn
Django Django is a framework that I
recommend to Founders that want to get
their prototypes done in no time it's
what they used to build Instagram and
it's something that you will love if you
felt like flask was a little bit too
featureless now whether you chose python
or JavaScript as your main weapon here
is where we all meet again because now
it's time to learn react JS react.js is
a library that makes building big
interactive applications on the browser
easier than if we did it only using
plain JavaScript we also have a free
react.js course as well click on the
description react.js has been around for
a while so the landscape is fairly
stable and there are some established
packages that are basically the industry
standard those packages are reactor
router for navigation styled components
for Styles re via query or aswr for data
fetching and recoiled also stand for
State Management I wish I could tell you
this is when it's overbought it isn't
now is when you specialize do you enjoy
working with node.js and express time to
learn typescript and check out nest.js
which is a more Enterprise web framework
we also made a course on that one didn't
like JavaScript or python time to maybe
learn Java spring or c-sharp did you
like working with react JS time to learn
next JS next JS makes the experience of
building react.js websites and absolute
pleasure if you enjoyed react.js and you
are interested in building IOS and
Android applications it is time to learn
react native which is almost the same as
the react that you are used to on the
web after you're done with all of this
you can call yourself a full stack
developer and I am a thousand percent
sure you will be able to get a job but
of course you gotta keep studying this
is when you need to do the the legwork
time to study data structures and
algorithms and time to learn SQL and
also time to learn a different
programming language maybe go maybe rust
maybe clutter something that will humble
you and make you a student again and
that is the roadmap I would follow if I
was going to become a full stack
developer today it does not mean is the
only one it's just an opinion based on
my personal experience I am sure that in
the comments you will find people that
say that you should start with Jabba
first or that beginners should learn SQL
right from the start everyone has a
different opinion everyone has a
different advice so try to keep your
mind open to all opinions and take the
best from each one of them I have seen
people follow this roadmap and get a job
so I know it works but other roadmaps
might work as well thank you for
watching this video let me know in the
comments what kind of content you would
like to see next and don't forget if you
like what you see please consider
leaving a like and subscribing it really
helps it's two clicks for you but it
helps me a lot stay free stay healthy be
happy eating
Hamida see you on the next one bye
[Music]